All previous creatine research has a
fatal flaw according to a brand new
study. This has been sent to me by so
many people willing to ditch their
creatine due to this new research. But
is that what the study actually
indicates? And are there some critical
nuances that change the scales back in
favor of creatine? The first answer is
yes. And so is the second answer. This
is going to be fun. Buckle up. In this
uh new study, researchers did what many
many other studies have done before.
Look at creatine's impact on muscle. But
they did something unique that few other
studies have done. And it's that unique
twist that makes this study so
influential. In a randomized control
design, the researchers had people
consume creatine or no creatine for 13
weeks. But instead of measuring muscle
or a semi-precise measure of muscle
known as lean body mass at the beginning
and then again at the end, they measured
again one week later. Then the
participants underwent the exact same
muscle building workout program for 12
weeks. This effectively keeps volume or
total amount of weight lifted the same
between groups. Other studies have just
measured at the beginning and then again
at the end. The reason this is uh
important is to measure one week later
again is because the creatine leads to
water retention which gets picked up in
lean body mass measures like those used
in many studies. So are people actually
gaining more lean body mass after taking
creatine and lifting weights or is it
merely initial water weight gain from
the creatine in the first week that
persists over time of the
study? Well, take a look. You can see
lean body mass change on the vertical
axis and then three measurements. The
baseline to washin indicates the
measurements after one week of creatine.
Notice that the creatine condition, the
darker bar, is statistically
significantly indicating creatine alone
leads to increases in lean body mass
without resistance training. And unless
it generates half a kilogram, about a
pound of lean mass, potentially muscle
in one week, and we found something
that's on par or more potent than
steroids, this is likely water weight
gain. So if we skip to the far right
where we compare the first baseline
measurement against 13 weeks later after
resistance training again, creatine
supplementation indicates a lean mass
increase compared to the control.
However, in the middle comparison,
they've removed the first week and
focused on the second baseline
measurement, the one after one week of
the likely water weight gain from
creatine supplementation. Notice how
creatine no longer offers an
advantage. Well, that's what all the
media headlines have been in a frenzy
about. Plainly, it tells us that lean
mass increases are only water weight,
not an actual lean mass increase from
the training effect on creatine. That's
pretty shocking, isn't it? I mean, so
many studies have told us that there's
advantages to creatine. So, was all that
research wrong due to such a critical
error in study
design? I wouldn't want to be someone
who's been saying that creatine is
effective for muscle and performance
right
now. Oh,
wait. Uh, I am. Um, well, I
uh uh it's getting uh getting pretty hot
in here, isn't it? Um, okay. I guess I
need to defend my honor. Unfortunately,
I left my suit of armor with my horse.
So, I'll need to use data instead. Talk
about nerdy. So, let me rewind and let
me remind you of something.
But instead of measuring muscle or a
semi-precise measure of muscle known as
lean body mass, the researchers did use
a measure that's extremely common in
research, DEXA, for lean body mass
measurements. But as I alluded to, it's
only a proxy since lean body mass is
made up of muscle, cartilage, and bone,
and many other tissues that are nonfat.
So it's assumed increases are largely
muscle, but they may not be. That is a
shortcoming of other research, but it's
also a silver bullet of this study. But
why if there wasn't even an increase in
lean body mass? Isn't it a moot point?
Well, not quite. Because the study used
a 12week training program, which might
be enough to detect muscle growth even
in lean body mass measures. But is it
sensitive to measure actual muscle
growth effects specifically? Maybe not.
But we don't need to speculate. I don't
need you to trust me. Although, well, a
little trust would be nice, but let's
not rely on it. There are studies that
measure muscle directly, not proxies. If
we pop open that data, we can see that
they make the same mistake as the many
other studies indicating in fat-ree
mass. So, FFM there, the creatine
condition indicates greater fat-ree
mass. But as we know, if we were to
remove the first week of water that's
sucked up into the musculature due to
creatine, we might not see these
effects. Fortunately, these researchers
also took muscle biopsies and measured
the actual size of individual muscle
cells as we see that here. the one 2 A
2A B and 2B there are different types of
muscle cells and clearly we see
significant increases in muscle cell
size. Now there's still two issues that
we need to address but fear not my
creatine dowsted honor shall be
vindicated. I'm going to be covering
more on creatine's impact on a muscle
from this study, including some nuances
of creatine that I think people aren't
considering in the extended version of
this video that you're currently
watching. If you'd be interested in
access to that along with live sessions
with me to chat up some studies, uh,
research reviews, and a whole library of
different study analyses and videos with
applicable takeaways, then join the
Physionic Insiders. The link is in the
description. Now, the first issue is
that increases in muscle cell size
doesn't actually speak to the
contractile units, the functional
proteins within the cells. I mean, we
know that the muscle itself gets an
outsized muscle size increase with
creatine, but that could still just be
water. Fortunately, there are many
studies looking at the effect of
creatine on these functional proteins
like measin and other myofibrillar
proteins and they still indicate a
creatine advantage. So now across
multiple lines of evidence, we still see
creatine have a musclepromoting effect.
But hey, why didn't we see at least some
change in the main study that we've been
discussing? Well, a number of reasons.
One, for the reasons that we discussed
earlier, lean body mass is imprecise for
muscle gain, although often used. But
more poignantly, when you're looking at
a small difference from a single
molecule, usually you need to do one or
two of three things. Increase the
precision of the test is one, but two is
to extend the length of the study. And
three, the researchers included enough
participants to detect differences in
lean body mass, but not necessarily by
something like direct muscle
measurements. There's a bit more on the
topic that I'll discuss in the insider
version if you're interested. So, where
does that leave everything? Should you
still be snorting creatine like Tony
Montana? Well, don't snort it. But this
study does illuminate a deficiency in
previous research. It's still an
important study. However, it does not
inform on the effectiveness of creatine
for muscle growth in as commanding a way
as has been portrayed by many. The
reality is even with this illuminating
discovery by the researchers, there's
still many lines of evidence, better
evidence that indicate that creatine
still promotes muscle growth. So, if
you're taking it for that outcome,
creatine is still a fantastic
supplement. But what are you doing
taking it for your muscles? I mean,
don't miss out on some of its other
benefits like those described here.
Thanks for hanging out and I got to go
snort some creatine.
[Music]